# Belachew Haile-Mariam Software Engineer

<u>belachewhm.github.io</u> belachewhm@gmail.com

# **Summary**

Full-Stack Software Engineer with progressive development experience. Proven technical background that includes experience in Software Engineering, DevOps, Automation, Production Support, and Distributed Systems. Excels in fast-paced environments with demonstrated skills in leading team projects while ensuring optimal business operations.

## **Technical Strengths**

Java Development Domain Driven Design Databases Web Development Event Driven Architecture Production Support Test Driven Development Test Driven Design Release Management

RESTful Web Services Distributed Systems DevOps

# **Experience**

## **United States Automobile Association (USAA)**

Software Engineer I | Bank Development Infrastructure | Plano, TX | September 2019 - Present

• Working in a team of software engineers to design and build solutions for the entire banking organization

## **Capital One**

Software Engineer | Emerging Products | Seattle, WA | April 2018 – September 2019

- Worked on the back end of a distributed system that utilized technologies such as Java, Spring Boot, Axon/CQRS, Docker, Kafka, Hystrix, and AWS to build micro-services and RESTful APIs
- Worked closely with business partners to groom our project backlog, create stories, define acceptance criteria, demonstrate completed stories, and ensure that all stories meet our definition of done before being worked on
- Reviewed API documentation of a third-party vendor and built customer on-boarding/account funding features
- Used Hystrix to add retry logic to parts of our system that interact with external services
- Integrated our system with DynamoDB global tables to ensure no duplication of processed events, and also to ensure a seamless system transition from one region to another in a disaster/failover scenario
- Built custom swagger meta-annotations to increase code-reuse and standardize API documentation
- On-boarded teams of developers to the back end of the project by creating technical documentation and leading a workshop where we discussed all relevant information required to start contributing to the project

#### Software Engineer | Home Loans Servicing | Plano, TX | April 2017 – March 2018

- Designed and implemented a testing solution that involved wrapping a Spring Boot application around existing Selenium/Cucumber test automation and exposing it as a set of RESTful web services and a custom SwaggerUI interface. The application was then Dockerized, and deployed to AWS for start of day production validations, infrastructure rehydrations, and L3 production support application monitoring
- Refactored and added new features to an internal application that tracks the progress of home loans as they move from the originations to servicing department. Angular Front end with a Java/Spring Back end
- Automated a manual internal audit process using Java, Splunk, and SQL. Splunk logs from our online portal were
  cross-referenced with loan boarding data to validate that only customers who clicked an "I accept" button on our
  terms and conditions page were enrolled in recurring payments. A PDF report was then generated outlining every
  loan that either passed or failed the audit
- Supporting production deployments, and testing/validating infrastructure rehydrations
- Resolved 234 production support tickets, including 212 customer digital escalations
- Built a Jira Dashboard using Jira queries and filters that tracked my team's progress on resolving customer digital escalations. This was extremely effective in helping us stay on top of incoming issues, and helped us reduce our ticket backlog in a timely and efficient manner
- Migrated Jenkins build jobs from an on-prem Jenkins 1.x instance to a Jenkins 2.x instance running on AWS
- Utilized GitHub, Jenkins, and cURL to automate part of our QA and Production deployments to AWS

#### **Fidelity Investments**

Software Engineer | Pricing and Cash Management Services | Westlake, TX | January 2017 – March 2017

- Reverse engineered a Java web application from a WAR file (created through an Ant build) into a multi-module Maven project, while simultaneously migrating the application from Subversion to Git. This shrunk the size of the code base down from over 4 GB to approximately 45 MB, and improved the speed and consistency of each build
- Wrote scripts to automatically download, install, and configure software on Windows machines
- Installed and configured Jenkins agents to run on virtual machines
- Migrated over 50 test automation source code repositories from SVN to Git, and renamed each project to follow a consistent naming convention to make them more easily identifiable
- Created a Maven parent project that defined clear and specific build goals for compilation, testing, packaging, installation, deployment, and reporting

Associate Software Engineer | Pricing and Cash Management Services | Westlake, TX | January 2016 – January 2017

- Developed a migration strategy to move development teams and their code repositories from Subversion to Git
- Facilitated training sessions to teach source control concepts using Git, Stash, SourceTree, and different development workflows (Central Repository, Feature Branches, Gitflow)
- Onboarded new and existing applications to CI/CD Jenkins pipelines, and modified existing pipelines as needed
- Worked in a development team to create and maintain a library of common test automation functions in Java
- Migrated Java applications from Ant to Maven
- Converted manual test cases into automated tests, and incorporated them into existing CI/CD pipelines

Associate Software Engineer | Leap Program | Cary, NC | August 2015 – December 2015

- Completed training modules on Object-Oriented Analysis & Design, UNIX Essentials, Oracle 11g & Data Modeling, Big Data, Java/XML, The Spring Framework, Service Oriented Architecture, Dynamic Web Applications, and C#
- Developed a system for Fidelity's Asset Management division to import, normalize, and store data from credit rating agencies into Hadoop. This allowed the firm to find credit rating mismatches between that information and data imported from credit rating aggregation services, saving the company millions of dollars in liabilities

Technical Intern | Pricing and Cash Management Services | Westlake, TX | June 2014 - August 2014

- Tested RESTful web services to measure latency, find security vulnerabilities, and ensure correct responses
- Constructed a web dashboard to showcase project overviews and associated metrics
- Managed and updated an online catalog of the services created

#### **Avoka Systems**

Web Application Developer Intern | Arlington, TX | June 2013 – May 2014

- Designed and built web applications using the Grails framework and MVC architecture
- Worked with customers to gather requirements and perform testing to verify that specifications were met

## **Education**

# The University of Texas at Arlington

Bachelor of Science | Computer Engineering | Arlington, TX | August 2010 - May 2015

- Senior Design Project Leader, Team SmartGrass
- Founding Father of the Theta-Omega Chapter of the Kappa Sigma Fraternity